Guide to the John Ahlquist and Margaret Levi Research Materials for the Book In the Interest of Others: Organizations and Social Activism
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
John Ahlquist and Margaret Levi research materials for the book In the Interest of Others: Organizations and Social Activism
2006-2012
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
5798
5798-001
5.57 cubic feet 8 boxes and 1 oversize folder
59 audio CDs; 2 DVDs
Audio files, DVDs of research material, correspondence, photographs and project records related to authors of the book In the Interest of Others: Organizations and Social Activism
John Ahlquist and Margaret Levi are authors of the book In the Interest of Others: Organizations and Social Activism. The book is a political science investigation that examines why some organizations expand their scope of action in ways that do not benefit their members directly. The working title of the research project was Union Democracy Reexamined.
In the book, John Ahlquist and Margaret Levi systematically compare and document eighty years of union social activism by the International Longshore and Warehouse Union (ILWU) in the United States and the Waterside Workers Federation (WWF) in Australia. They compare the ILWU and WWF to the Teamsters and the International Longshoremen's Association, two American transport industry labor unions that actively discouraged the pursuit of political causes unrelated to their own economic interests.
John S. Ahlquist is the Trice Family Faculty Scholar and associate professor of political science at the University of Wisconsin in Madison. He is also a research associate in political economy at the United States Studies Centre at the University of Sydney and a faculty affiliate of the La Follette School, the Center for Financial Security, and the Institute for Research on Poverty. He holds a B.A. from UC Berkeley and a Ph.D. from the University of Washington. Ahlquist was project director for the Union Democracy Reexamined project while he was a graduate student at the University of Washington.
Margaret Levi is the Jere L. Bacharach Professor of International Studies at the University of Washington and Senior Fellow, Watson Institute of International Studies, Brown University. She is Foundational Chair in Politics at the University of Sydney's United States Studies Centre, where she is now an Affiliate Professor. She is also Director of the CHAOS (Comparative Historical Analysis of Organizations and States) Center and formerly the Harry Bridges Chair and Director, the Harry Bridges Center for Labor Studies. Levi earned her B.A. from Bryn Mawr College in 1968 and her Ph.D. from Harvard University in 1974, the year she joined the faculty of the University of Washington. She became a Fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences in 2001 and a John Simon Guggenheim Fellow in 2002. She was a Phi Beta Kappa Visiting Scholar (2006-7) and recipient of the S. Sterling Munro Public Service Teaching Award in 2001. She served as President of the American Political Science Association (2004-5).
Photocopied archival material, audio files, DVDs of research materials, surveys to ILWU members, correspondence, and project records.
Research materials for the book In the Interest of Others: Organizations and Social Activism and the Union Democracy Reexamined Project. Much of the material is photocopies of primary source collections from other repositories such as the Noel Butlin Archives in Australia and the Ann Rand Research Library and Archives at the ILWU International's office in San Francisco. As well, there are many photocopies from other collections in the University of Washington Special Collections. The materials include DVDs of audio files of interviews on longshore workers by Howard Kimeldorf for his book Reds or Rackets? and William Finlay for his book Work on the Waterfront. Other materials include DVDs of Waterside Workers Federation of Australia films and posters.
Open to all users but access to some portions of the collection are restricted. Contact Special Collections for more information.
Donated by Margaret Levi.
Ahlquist, John S., and Margaret Levi. 2013. In the interest of others: organizations and social activism.
"In the interest of others: organizations and social activism," Ahlquist, John S., and Margaret Levi. Accessed November 19, 2013, http://depts.washington.edu/ilwu
Ahlquist, John S.$vArchives; Levi, Margaret$vArchives; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington)
Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor History; Photographs; Sound Recordings; Electronic Records
- UNION DEMOCRACY REEXAMINED PROJECT RESEARCH FILES, SERIES I
  Research files on the International Longshore and Warehouse Union, the International Longshoremen's Association, the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, and the Waterside Workers Federation of Australia
  - Survey Forms, Subseries A (Box 6-7)
    Restricted
    These surveys can only be accessed with written permission from both the current ILWU President and Margaret Levi.
    Surveys administered to members of ILWU locals to assess attitudes toward the union, its political culture, and their own occupational histories.
  - Longshore Oral History Interviews, Subseries B (Box 8/1-8/60)
    Oral History Interviews with ILWU members and people involved in the union.
    - Darcy, Sam Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2, c. May 10, 1986 (Box-folder 8/1)
    - Darcy, Sam Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 3 and 4, c. May 10, 1986 (Box-folder 8/2)
    - Erkkila, Reino Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2 (Box-folder 8/3)
    - Erkkila, Reino Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 3, 4 (Box-folder 8/4)
    - "Mevea" [Mervert, Elmer, Oscar Hagen, and Don Meyers?] Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 3 (Box-folder 8/5)
    - "Mevea" [Mervert, Elmer, Oscar Hagen, and Don Meyers?] Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2 (Box-folder 8/6)
    - Yoneda, Karl; Elaine Yoneda Black Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2 (Box-folder 8/7)
    - Yoneda, Karl; Elaine Yoneda Black Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 3, 5 (Box-folder 8/8)
    - Bulcke, Germaine Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2, c. September 4, 1981 (Box-folder 8/9)
    - Bulcke, Germaine Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 3, 4, c. September 4, 1981 (Box-folder 8/10)
    - Bulcke, Germaine Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 5, 6, c. September 4, 1981 (Box-folder 8/11)
    - Bulcke, Germaine Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 7, c. September 4, 1981 (Box-folder 8/12)
    - Craycraft, Rosco Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2, c. December 16, 1981 (Box-folder 8/13)
    - Craycraft, Rosco Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 3, 4, c. December 16, 1981 (Box-folder 8/14)
    - Osborne, Seldon Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2, c. September 11, 1981 (Box-folder 8/15)
    - Osborne, Seldon Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 3, 4, c. September 11, 1981 (Box-folder 8/16)
    - Osborne, Seldon Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 5, 6, c. September 11, 1981 (Box-folder 8/17)
    - Retirees Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2 (Box-folder 8/18)
    - Retirees Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 3, 4 (Box-folder 8/19)
    - Richardson, Fred Gus Rystad Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2, c. December 18, 1981 (Box-folder 8/20)
    - Richardson, Fred Gus Rystad Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 3, 4, c. December 18, 1981 (Box-folder 8/21)
    - Harer, Asher Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2, c. May 25, 1982 (Box-folder 8/22)
    - Harer, Asher, Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 3, 4, c. May 25, 1982 (Box-folder 8/23)
    - Langley, Al Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2, c. February 4, 1982 (Box-folder 8/24)
    - Langley, Al Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 3, c. February 4, 1982 (Box-folder 8/25)
    - Weir, Stanley Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2, c. April 22, 1981 (Box-folder 8/26)
    - Weir, Stanley Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 3, 4, c. April 22, 1981 (Box-folder 8/27)
    - Weir, Stanley Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 5, 6, c. April 22, 1981 (Box-folder 8/28)
    - Schmidt, Henry Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2, c. January 25, 1984 (Box-folder 8/29)
    - Schmidt, Henry Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 3, 4, c. January 25, 1984 (Box-folder 8/30)
    - Fairley, Lincoln Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2 (Box-folder 8/31)
    - Fairley, Lincoln Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 3, 4 (Box-folder 8/32)
    - Fairley, Lincoln Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 5, 6 (Box-folder 8/33)
    - Morris, George Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2, c. September 2, 1980 (Box-folder 8/34)
    - Morris, George Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 3, 4, c. September 2, 1980 (Box-folder 8/35)
    - Mowrey, Jack Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2, c. September 2, 1980 (Box-folder 8/36)
    - Mowrey, Jack Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 3, c. September 2, 1980 (Box-folder 8/37)
    - Werner, Joe Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2, c. December 14, 1981; July 25, 1985 (Box-folder 8/38)
    - Werner, Joe Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 3, 4, c. December 14, 1981; July 25, 1985 (Box-folder 8/39)
    - Werner, Joe Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 5, 6, c. December 14, 1981; July 25, 1985 (Box-folder 8/40)
    - Werner, Joe Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 7, c. December 14, 1981; July 25, 1985 (Box-folder 8/41)
    - Werner, Joe Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2 7-15-85, c. December 14, 1981; July 25, 1985 (Box-folder 8/42)
    - Brown, Archie Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2, c. September 12, 1981; September 7, 1982 (Box-folder 8/43)
    - Brown, Archie Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 3, 4, c. September 12, 1981; September 7, 1982 (Box-folder 8/44)
    - Brown, Archie Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 5, 6, c. September 12, 1981; September 7, 1982 (Box-folder 8/45)
    - Brown, Archie Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 7, c. September 12, 1981; September 7, 1982 (Box-folder 8/46)
    - Brown, Archie Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2, c. September 12, 1981; September 7, 1982 (Box-folder 8/47)
    - Brown, Archie Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Side 3, c. September 12, 1981; September 7, 1982 (Box-folder 8/48)
    - Brown, Archie Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Side 3, c. September 12, 1981; September 7, 1982 (Box-folder 8/49)
    - Yanow, Harold Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2 (Box-folder 8/50)
    - Yanow, Harold Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2 (Box-folder 8/51)
    - Stack, Walter Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2, c. May 28, 1982 (Box-folder 8/52)
    - Ware, Paul Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2, c. January 23, 1982 (Box-folder 8/53)
    - Ware, Paul Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 3, 4, c. January 23, 1982 (Box-folder 8/54)
    - Bailey, Bill Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2, c. September 15, 1981 (Box-folder 8/55)
    - Bailey, Bill Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 3, 4, c. September 15, 1981 (Box-folder 8/56)
    - Bailey, Bill Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 5, 6, c. September 15, 1981 (Box-folder 8/57)
    - Baylin, Meyer Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides: 1, 2, c. January 23, 1984 (Box-folder 8/58)
    - Baylin, Meyer Interview by Howard Kimeldorf, Sides 3, 4, c. January 23, 1984 (Box-folder 8/59)
    - Bridges, Harry Oral History (Box-folder 8/60)
  - Waterside Workers Federation of Australia, Subseries C (Box 8/61-8/63)
    DVDs of posters and films on the Waterside Workers Federation of Australia.
    - DVD: Waterside Workers Federation of Australia Materials (Box-folder 8/61)
    - DVD: Waterside Workers Federation of Australia Materials (Box-folder 8/62)
    - DVD: Waterside Workers Federation of Australia Films (Box-folder 8/63)